<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Engine on Tempest Engine Dev</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/engine/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Engine on Tempest Engine Dev</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 08:40:45 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/engine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Asset System</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/asset-system/asset-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 08:40:45 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/asset-system/asset-system/</guid>
      <description>Table of Contents Assets AssetLifetime AssetRegistry Cooking CookOnTheFly OfflineCooking Assets The Tempest engine, like most other engines out there, has a concept of an asset along with an asset manager that can handle asset lifetimes as well as asset cooking. The engine contains a base class that all asset types derive from. A simplified version of that Asset base class is below.&#xA;struct AssetHandle { // This contains the unique path to the asset, stored as a string // and a hash value of that path evaluated at compile time using constexpr.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tempest Engine</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/tempest-engine/tempest-engine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 06:40:54 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/tempest-engine/tempest-engine/</guid>
      <description>Table of Contents Introduction Why Build A New Engine Pros Cons Conclusion Introduction About two years ago I had started building a new engine in C++ with the initial intention of having some base framework I could experiment with and also challenging myself to build a proper game editor since I had yet to do that. I had built a few engines in the past but it was always with the intention of learning more things so I generally avoided using third party libraries.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
